How's it going everyone? This video is
going to be over one system or trading
strategy that you can follow in 2026.
Too many people bounce around from model
to model and then cannot find
consistency simply due to the fact that
they cannot follow a single system.
Let's go ahead and learn my fractal
model. Now, this model is built off the
fact that price cannot reverse without a
swing point. If price is going to go
from a bearish trend to a bullish trend,
it's going to form a bullish swing
point. If it's going from a bullish
trend to a bearish trend, it's going to
form a bearish swing point. Now, if we
look for these swing points to form at a
point of interest and look for certain
candle closures, we can anticipate
expansion candles that follow. Now, the
first thing we need to do before we get
into the lower time frames is come into
the day with a daily bias. We're going
to do this by simply looking at the
daily closure. If price has a closure
outside the range, we're going to be
looking for a continuation. So, you can
see here with a bullish continuation,
price closes over its previous day high.
So, I'm looking for price to continue
higher. And here you can see with the
bearish continuation, price closes below
its previous day low. So, I'd be looking
for a continuation lower with a reversal
closure. We have price sweeping out its
previous day low and closing back above
that low, showing that price has
reversed off that low. And we can
anticipate a continuation higher in the
next day with a bearish reversal. Price
has taken out its previous day high,
closed back below that level, and then I
can be looking for a continuation that
following day. So once I have a daily
bias, then I'm going to look for
structure and a swing point formation.
So how do I go about this? Well, here
you can see we have a bullish daily bias
through previous day high as price has
closed over its previous candle's high.
So looking for that, I'm going to be
looking for a point of interest for
price to react out of. So I'm going to
look for that in the previous range of
the previous day. So here you can see
looking in this range here, we have a
fair value gap. Now points of interest
are always going to be either a fair
value gap or a low in a bullish scenario
or a fair value gap and a high in a
bearish scenario. Then I'm going to want
to wait for price to reach into that
point of interest and have either a
candle 2 or a candle 3 closure, which if
you don't know what those are, I do have
videos on those topics. So here you can
see we have expansion, price retraces
into this fair value gap, has a candle 2
closure, and we have a draw on
liquidity, which is our previous day
high. So with this, I would want to go
down to the lower time frames, and then
I'd look for a fractal model. Now, very
simply, we're going to go down to the
lower time frames using our time frame
alignment. So, for instance, if that
swing point was on the hourly, I'd be
using the 5minut. If it's on the 30
minute, I'd be using the 3minut. Now,
we're going to check to make sure we
have a change in the state of delivery,
which confirms the swing point, but
we're not going to enter on that change
in the state of delivery. We're going to
wait for another continuation. So, what
I'm going to do is let some structure
form here. You can see we sweep out a
low into a fair value up. So, we have
that point of interest and then we get
the close through the series of downclo
candles. This is a continuation order
block which I also have a video on. Once
I have a continuation order block that
forms going to look to enter on that
close through my stop on that protected
low and then look for 2 R. So just to
review if we go back through this we're
going to get a daily bias. In this case
it was bullish. We'll then look for
hourly structure or a point of interest
on my desired time frame to be looking
for. Some people prefer that on the
4hour or even the 30 minute. And then
from there when we form a candle 2 or a
candle three closure in that point of
interest, I'll go down to the lower time
frame using the time frame pairing and
then look for a continuation order block
and look for 2R. So now that you
understand this system, let's go through
a few examples of this. So here we are
in our first example and you can see we
have taken out all the highs over here
to our left and then we have a bunch of
failure swings and a fair value gap
here. So when we have multiple days of
an expansion without a new swing point,
I can be looking for a retracement or a
reversal. Here you can see on the daily
chart, we do have that reversal closure.
So that gives me bias bearish into this
next day and I could be looking for
price to trade into this daily fair
value gap below. Now let's go down to
the hourly time frame for our structure.
So here we are on the hourly time frame.
You can see we have a change in the
state of delivery as we have price
sweeping out the highs right here and
then closing through the series of
upclose candles and that's validating
this swing point. So now going into the
next day, we'd want to look at the lower
half of this previous day's range and
look for price to form its wick. So we'
be looking for a candle 2 closure or a
candle 3 closure in here to try to get
on side if I want to catch the wick or
wait for a continuation. So let's see if
we can find either of those. So here you
can see we do have a reversal closure
but it's not very bearish, right? It's
more of a dogee. But we can go down to
the 5minut time frame and see what this
looks like. Now down here on the 5minut
time frame, what would we want to see?
We'd want to see the lower half of this
change in the state of delivery be
respected if price is going to continue
lower in the next candle. And here you
can see price trades rather high
creating equal highs up here. So this is
not something I'd be interested in
shorting. Let's see what would happen.
So you can see it just more so
consolidates and then runs out the high.
Let's go back to our structured time
frame as that would not provide a valid
setup. Let's see if we can find a new
swing point or if it trades too high, we
can see if it reverses and then look for
a continuation.
So here you can see price has traded
rather high. So it's very hard for me to
trust this reversal so close to this
high. I would want to see if price can
form a nice V-shaped reversal and then
look for a continuation. Otherwise, many
times I see this just fail and then run
out the swing point. Let's get some more
information.
And here you see we start to get that
displacement down or that V-shaped
reversal. Now, that is very aggressive.
And you can see this is a new
continuation or a continuation order
block on the structure time frame. So,
let's continue to look at this time
frame and see if we can get a
retracement to get on side with a move.
Now, one thing to notice here is we do
have this bullish reversal, but this
bullish reversal then fails as we are
forming a candle to closure bearish
here. And now this is located within a
fair value gap right here. It's rather
small, but a fair value gap and
retesting this continuation order block.
So, we could go down to the lower time
frame and see if the structure aligns
with a move towards previous day low and
into that daily fair value gap. Let's
drop down to the 5minut time frame as
that aligns with the hourly. So, here we
are down on the 5minut time frame. And
let's take a look. Do we have a point of
interest here? We do. We have a fair
value gap. But what else are we doing?
We're taking out this short-term low
here. So, this is where we sometimes
will run out a protected swing or a new
high to then go lower. Let's give this
another candle or two. And you can see
we don't respect this area at all or
this smallbodied candle here. So, let's
see if we form a new continuation.
So, we are sweeping out that high. We
then need it to form a continuation
which would be a close below here. Let's
see if we can get that.
And there you can see we do get the
closure below. So then I could look to
take a position either on the close or
on the retest. Put my stop on the body
high or the actual high. Either one
works. That is up to you. And then I'd
be looking for two R. So just to review,
we have a daily bias that is bearish. We
have an hourly continuation out of a
fair value gap. So we have formed the
high of the day is what I'm anticipating
and then a continuation in this hourly
fair value gap right here. And then we
have a continuation on the lower time
frames. So what are we doing? We are
aligning all of our time frames in one
direction. The daily is bearish, the
hourly is bearish, and the 5m minute is
bearish. This is when expansion can
occur. So let's see what happens. We get
tagged in on the retest. Candle four, do
we get a continuation? It waits until
candle five, but we do get a move lower,
right? And that is the expansion that
occurs when we have all time frames
aligned bearish. So, just to review one
more time, we'll go back out to the
daily time frame. Here we have price
taking out highs on the left. Here we
have a reversal closure, which gives us
a bearish bias for this day. here going
down to the hourly time frame. We have a
change in the state of delivery which
confirms that daily bearish swing point
and then we are looking for the wick
high to form in this daily candle. Now I
can look to trade it on the candle
closure and actually get in on the wick
or I can let that in candle change in
the state of delivery form or that
continuation on the structure time frame
and then seek a continuation. Here price
traded too high so we let a V-shaped
reversal form then looked to get a
retracement and then get on side with a
new expansion. So here you can see we
had a candle to closure and a point of
interest and then we went down to the
lower time frames and found a
continuation order block. Now where
could I be targeting instead of just two
R here. I could look for previous day
low or for price to trade into that
daily fair value gap below. And you can
see if we let that play out, we do get a
very nice drop into that daily fair
value gap. And that's how you can get
greater risk-to-reward on your trades is
use a lower time frame invalidation and
still target those higher time frame
objectives. Now, let's get into another
example. Now, here we are on our next
example. We are on USD JPY on the daily
and monthly time frame. Here you can see
we've had a candle to closure on the
monthly, which gives us a bullish bias
for this month or this October. Now,
we're getting into the end of October. I
don't want to fade that month,
especially with these equal highs
resting above. So, with equal highs,
what do we have? We have a candle to
closure on this time frame. So, what
would we want to do here? Well, we'd
want to refine that down and confirm it.
Now, this is a fractal concept. So, in
the earlier example, I use the daily,
hourly, and 5m minute. But here, you can
see I'm using the monthly, daily, and
then hourly. So, the hourly will be my
entry time frame. Now, is this at a
point of interest? Yes, it has wretched
into this fair value gap here. The body
is respecting it and we are closing back
above it. So, instead of going all the
way down to my lower time frames in this
case, I can just use the hourly as my
entry time frame. Does that mean you
can't refine this down further? Of
course, you can, but sometimes I just
prefer to not refine it down too much.
But let's see here. What do we want to
see? We want to see price open and then
form a continuation, right? We're
looking for a continuation order block.
Now, if we look in this structure here,
I already have one, but I don't want to
see price trade below this level, right?
And that also lines up with the EQ.
Let's look for another continuation to
form in here.
Now, we do have a fair value gap here,
right? We reach into a fair value gap.
Do we close over these down close
candles to form a continuation? No. We
are forming a consolidation and then we
make a new low. Now I've refined this
down. Do we close over this level to
form a new continuation
and there we do. So with that I can then
look to take an entry either on the
retest or the close here. I'd rather
take it on the retest. Why is that?
Well, we just took out these highs here.
So we could get a retracement before
going higher. So looking for a retest,
put my stop on the bodies because they
are nice and fullbodied candles. And
then look for 2 R. Let's see how this
works out.
And there we hit 2R. You can see this is
an example of the monthly to daily to
hourly framework, right? Just aligning
multiple time frames in one direction.
Now, if I wanted to refine this down
further, I could look to refine this
down in here as price takes out this
high and then we have a retracement. So,
if we're going to continue higher, I'd
expect a low to form in here to trade
higher, which you could look for a swing
point on the 30 or 15minut time frames.
So let's get into one more final
example. So here we are in one more
example. We are on oil on the hourly
chart. So you can see we have this daily
closure here which is bearish and then
do we have that change in the state of
delivery? And we do. We have closed
through that level. Now we want to look
for a continuation in this area to get
on side with it. You can see it's a bit
messy, right? We have all these failure
swings. We have swept out this
short-term low here. So it's not looking
great, but let's see if we can find
something. You can see we'd want to see
this area respected and price just
immediately trades higher.
Now you can see we do sweep out this
little low but even with that do we form
a continuation? No, we do not. We have
not closed below this level
and we fail to do so. So now what is
this becoming?
When we fail to form a continuation
multiple times, this is just becoming a
range, right? This is a consolidation.
So, how do we approach consolidations?
Well, we'd want to see the high or the
low of the range be taken out and then a
continuation or an order block form
there. Here you can see we sweep out the
high in this consolidation or previous
days high. We now have a protected swing
form and then we could look for price to
continue lower here. Now, I just wanted
to show this example because one, if we
are not going to form a continuation, it
doesn't always occur. That is where
price will then form a consolidation.
and then I want to avoid it until one
side of the range is taken. If I do want
to trade something like this, this is
trading a reversal day, which is a bit
more complex. But that is how I would
approach it. Now, let's say I did want
to get on side here. Well, I can still
look to trade a continuation. So, if I
go down to the 15-minute time frame
here, you can see we have that sweep and
the close through and we form another
continuation or this breakdown here,
which I could trade the breakout of. But
this is not an example of something that
I want to trade. I was more so showing
this to show you that when price fails
to form a continuation and you are
looking for it or it is just messy.
Don't try to force yourself on the
market. Focus on those examples that are
really clear and focus on trading those
versus trading something like this
because it's just a bit more complex.
Now, if you did enjoy this video, please
let me know in the comments below and
I'll see you guys next week. Have a good
one.